Guide to the Otto Rank Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series IV: Arranged Manuscripts
  - Subseries IV.3: Book Reviews
    - Book Review of Technik derPsychoanalyse, [n.p.], May 1931, (45 page t.ms. (journal)) (Box 26, Folder 399)
    - Book Review of Technik der Psychoanalyse, [n.p.], 14 March 1927, (34 page t.ms. (journal)) (Box 26, Folder 400)
    - Sachs, Hans Book Review of Das Trauma der Geburt, (4 page t.ms.) (Box 26, Folder 401)
    - Book Review of Das Trauma der Geburt. In English., [n.p.], 1924, (4 page t.ms.) (Box 26, Folder 402)
    - Book Review of Wahrheit und Wirklichkeit, [n.p.], 1929, (1 page a.ms.) (Box 26, Folder 403)
    - Miscellaneous book reviews, (12 page newspaper clippings) (Box 26, Folder 404)
- Series V: Arranged Photographs and Drawings
  - Photographs and sketches, (8 photos, 2 drawings) (Box 27, Folder 405)
  - Rank photographs- Duplicates of Bachrach photo, (6 duplicate photos, 1 t.ms.) (Box 27, Folder 406)
  - Photographs of Otto Rank, (1 photo) (Box 27, Folder 407)
    [1985 gift]
  - Photograph of Otto Rank, (1 photo) (Box 27, Folder 408)
    [Gift of E. J. Lieberman, 1990]
  - Carpenter drawings, (3 pages) (Box 27, Folder 409)
- Series VI: Printed Series
  - Subseries VI.1: Clippings
    - Clippings 1916, [n.p.], 1916, (16 page newspapers and magazines) (Box 28, Folder 410)
    - Clippings. 1923-27., (12 page newspapers) (Box 28, Folder 410a)
    - Clippings A-C, (250 page newspapers and magazines) (Box 28, Folder 411)
      [See Manuscript Flat Box 172. O.R.A. gift 1984]
    - Clippings D-L, (190 page newspapers and clippings) (Box 28, Folder 412)
    - Clippings M-R, (185 page newspapers and magazines) (Box 28, Folder 413)
      [See Manuscript Flat Box 173. O.R.A. gift 1984.]
    - Clippings. Science, Semantics, State., (160 page newspapers and magazines) (Box 28, Folder 414)
    - Clippings. Women, Women and Economics., (100 page newspapers and magazines) (Box 28, Folder 415)
    - Clippings. Economy., (7 page newspapers and magazines) (Box 28, Folder 416)
      [See Manuscript Flat Box 172. O.R.A. gift 1984.]
    - Clippings. Mark Twain., (15 page newspapers and magazines) (Box 28, Folder 417)
      [See Manuscript Flat Box 173. O.R.A. gift, 1984.]
    - Clippings. WW I., (20 page newspapers and magazines) (Box 28, Folder 418)
    - Clippings. German literature & history., (60 page newspapers and magazines) (Box 28, Folder 419)
    - Clippings. 1933-1938., (100 page newspapers and magazines) (Box 28, Folder 420)
  - Subseries VI.2: Books
    - Rank, Otto & Sachs, Hans Die Bedeutung der Psychoanalyse fur die Geisteswissenschaften, [n.p.], 1913, (111 pages) (Box 29, Folder 421)
      [Velfort Gift 1989]
    - Rank, Otto & Ferenczi, S&or The Development of Psychoanalysis. First English edition of Entwicklungsziele der Psychoanaylse., New York, 1925, (70 pages) (Box 29, Folder 422)
    - Rank, Otto Die Don Juan Gestalt. Second edition., Leipzig, 1924, (83 pages) (Box 29, Folder 423)
      [Velfort gift, 1989]
    - Rank, Otto La Figura del Don Giovanni. Italian edition of Don Juan., [n.p.], 1987, (121 pages) (Box 29, Folder 424)
    - Rank, Otto Une etude sur le double. French edition of Don Juan & Doppelganger., Paris, 1932, (265 pages) (Box 29, Folder 425)
    - Rank, Otto Der Doppelganger (Box 29, Folder 426)
    - Rank, Otto Der Doppelganger, [n.p.], 1925, (117 pages) (Box 29, Folder 426)
    - Rank, Otto Der Doppelganger, [n.p.], 1925, (117 pages) (Box 29, Folder 427)
    - Rank, Otto The Double. English edition of Der Doppelganger., [n.p.], 1971, (86 pages) (Box 29, Folder 428)
    - Rank, Otto Ein Traum, der sick selbst deutet, [n.p.], [1910], (75 pages) (Box 30, Folder 429)
    - Rank, Otto & Ferenczi, S&or Entwicklungsziele der Psychoanalyse, [n.p.], 1924, (67 pages) (Box 30, Folder 430)
    - Rank, Otto Erziehung und Weltanschuung, [n.p.], 1933, (183 pages) (Box 30, Folder 431)
    - Rank, Otto Genetische Psychologie. Parts I & II. English translation., [n.p.], 1927, 1928, (144 pages) (Box 30, Folder 432)
      [Mimeograph. See folder 472 for addional copy.]
    - Rank, Otto Geneitsche Psychologie. Parts I & II. English translation., [n.p.], 1927, 1928, (172 pages) (Box 30, Folder 433)
      [Mimeograph. See folder 472 for additional copy.]
    - Rank, Otto Outlines of a Genetic Psychology. (Box 30, Folder 433a)
      [See box 38, folder 472.]
    - Rank, Otto Grundzuge einer Genetischen Psychologie. Vol I & II., [n.p.], 1927, (103 pages) (Box 30, Folder 434)
      [See box 40a for additional copy.]
    - Rank, Otto Das Inzest-Motiv in Dichhung und Sage. First edition., [n.p.], [1912], (685 pages) (Box 31, Folder 435)
      [Some annotations. Velfort gift 1989.]
    - Rank, Otto Das Inzest-Motiv in Dichtung und Sage. Second edition., [n.p.], 1926, (465 pages) (Box 31, Folder 436)
    - Rank, Otto Der Kustler. Second and third editions., [n.p.], 1918, (84 pages) (Box 32, Folder 437)
      [Velfort gift 1989. See box 40a for additional edition.]
    - Rank, Otto Der Kunstler. Fourth edition., [n.p.], 1925, (208 pages) (Box 32, Folder 438)
      [Velfort gift 1989]
    - Rank, Otto Der Kunstler. Fourth edition., [n.p.], 1925, (208 pages) (Box 32, Folder 439)
    - Rank, Otto Kunst und Kunstler. English translation [Art and Artist]., [n.p.], 1932, (431 pages) (Box 32, Folder 440)
    - Rank, Otto Die Lohengrinsage, [n.p.], 1911, (182 pages) (Box 32, Folder 441)
    - Rank, Otto Der Mythus von der Geburt des Helden, [n.p.], 1909, (93 pages) (Box 32, Folder 442)
      [Numerous notations by Rank (?). Velfort gift 1989.]
    - Rank, Otto Der Mythus ov der Geburt des Helden, [n.p.], 1922, (160 pages) (Box 33, Folder 443)
    - Rank, Otto Der Mythus. English translation. [The Myth of the Birth of the Hero]., [n.p.], 1952, (100 pages) (Box 33, Folder 444)
    - Rank, Otto Eine Neurosenanalyse in Traumen, [n.p.], 1924, (231 pages) (Box 33, Folder 445)
    - Rank, Otto Psychoanalytische Beitrage zur Mythenforschung, [n.p.], 1919, (420 pages) (Box 33, Folder 446)
    - Rank, Otto Psychoanalytische Beitrage zur Mythenforschung. Second edition., [n.p.], 1922, (184 pages) (Box 34, Folder 447)
    - Rank, Otto Seelenglaube und Psychologie, [n.p.], 1930, (193 pages) (Box 34, Folder 448)
      [Velfort gift 1989. See box 40a for additonal edition and English translation.]
    - Rank, Otto Sexualitat und Schuldgefuhe, [n.p.], 1926, (160 pages) (Box 34, Folder 449)
    - Rank, Otto Tagebuchblatter eines Totgeborenen, (4 pages) (Box 35, Folder 450)
    - Rank, Otto Das Trauma der Geburt, [n.p.], 1924, (200 p [?]. pages) (Box 35, Folder 451)
      [See box 40a for an additional editions.]
    - Rank, Otto Das Trauma der Geburt, [n.p.], 1924, (202 pages) (Box 35, Folder 452)
      [Simon gift 1990]
    - Rank, Otto Das Trauma der Geburt. Italian edition., [n.p.], 1972, (211 pages) (Box 35, Folder 453)
    - Rank, Otto Das Trauma der Geburt, [n.p.], 1988, (220 pages) (Box 35, Folder 454)
    - Rank, Otto Das Trauma der Geburt, Giessen, 1988, (207 pages) (Box 35, Folder 454 A)
      [Gift 1998]
    - Rank, Otto Das Trauma der Geburt. English trans. [The Trauma of Birth]., [n.p.], 1952, (223 pages) (Box 35, Folder 455)
    - Rank, Otto Technik der Psychoanalyse. Vol I., [n.p.], 1926, (211 pages) (Box 36, Folder 456)
    - Rank, Otto Technik der Psychoanalyse. Vol. I., [n.p.], 1926, (211 pages) (Box 36, Folder 457)
    - Rank, Otto Technik der Psychoanalyse. Vol. I., [n.p.], 1926, (211 pages) (Box 36, Folder 458)
    - Rank, Otto Technik der Psychoanalyse. Vol. I., [n.p.], 1926, (211 pages) (Box 36, Folder 459)
    - Rank, Otto Technik der Psychoanalyse. Vol. II., [n.p.], 1929, (121 pages) (Box 36, Folder 460)
      [Simon gift 1990. See box 40a for English translation.]
    - Rank, Otto Technik der Psychoanalyse. Vol II., [n.p.], 1929, (121 pages) (Box 36, Folder 461)
    - Rank, Otto Technik der Psychoanalyse. Vol. I - III., [n.p.], 1926, (472 pages) (Box 37, Folder 462)
    - Rank, Otto Technik der Psychoanalyse. Vol. III., [n.p.], 1931, (139 pages) (Box 37, Folder 463)
    - Rank, Otto Technik der Psychoanalyse. Vol. III., [n.p.], 1931, (139 pages) (Box 37, Folder 464)
    - Rank, Otto Technik der Psychoanalyse. Vol. III., [n.p.], 1931, (139 pages) (Box 37, Folder 465)
    - Rank, Otto Technik der Psychoanalyse. Vol. III., [n.p.], 1931, (139 pages) (Box 37, Folder 466)
    - Rank, Otto Volkerpsychologische Parallelen, [n.p.], 1912, (24 pages) (Box 38, Folder 467)
      [Some annotations. Simon gift 1990.]
    - Rank, Otto Warheit und Wirklichkeit, [n.p.], 1929, (112 pages) (Box 38, Folder 468)
    - Rank, Otto Warheit und Wirlichkeit, [n.p.], 1929, (112 pages) (Box 38, Folder 469)
    - Rank, Otto Wahrheit und Wirlichkeit. Italian trans. [La volonta di essere felici]., (189 pages) (Box 38, Folder 470)
    - Rank, Otto Warheheit und Wirlichkeit. Italian trans. [La volonta die essere felici]., (189 pages) (Box 38, Folder 471)
    - Rank, Otto Genetische Psychology. English trans. [Outlines of a Genetic Psychology]., [n.p.], 1927, (172 pages) (Box 38, Folder 472)
      [See folders 432 & 433]
    - Arnold, T. W. The Symbols of Government, [n.p.], 1935, (278 pages) (Box 39, Folder 473)
      [Some notes by Rank (?)]
    - Rank, Otto Theory and Therapy. An Introduction to the Psychology of Otto Rank., [n.p.], 1935, (38 pages) (Box 39, Folder 474)
    - Bischler, W. La Psychologie de M. Otto Rank, [n.p.], 1934, (37 pages) (Box 39, Folder 475)
    - Faatz, Anita The nature of choice in casework process, [n.p.], 1953, (141 pages) (Box 39, Folder 476)
    - Freud, Sigmund Der Mann Moses und die monotheistische Religion, [n.p.], 1939, (241 pages) (Box 39, Folder 477)
    - Freud, Sigmund Zur Psychopathologie des Alltagslebens, [n.p.], 1907, (132 pages) (Box 39, Folder 478)
    - Freud, Sigmund Die Traumdeutung. Seventh edition., [n.p.], 1922, (478 pages) (Box 39, Folder 479)
      [See additional copies in box 40b]
    - Louys, Pierre Contes Choisis, (91 pages) (Box 40, Folder 480)
    - Moustakas, Clark. ed. The Self: Explorations in Personal Growth, [n.p.], 1956, (284 pages) (Box 40, Folder 481)
    - Novey, Riva Otto Rank: Beginnings, endings and current experience, [n.p.], 1981, (16 pages) (Box 40, Folder 482)
    - Robinson, Virgina The Development of a Professional Self, [n.p.], 1978, (437 pages) (Box 40, Folder 483)
    - Sachs, Hans Freud, mon maitre mon ami. [n.p.], 1977. [Original 1944], (171 pages) (Box 40, Folder 484)
    - Shakespeare Sonnets, [n.p.], 1938, (80 pages) (Box 40, Folder 485)
    - Szekely-Kovacs, O. & Bereny, R. Karikaturen, [n.p.], 1924, (125 p (?). pages) (Box 40, Folder 486)
  - Subseries VI.3: Additional Printed Material
    - Rank, Otto Various books by Otto Rank, Various places, Various dates, (10 books pages) (Box 40a)
      [See individual records to see which ones are enclosed]
    - Otto Rank, Sigmund Freud Books by Rank & Freud, journals of O.R.A. & Anais, Various places, Various dates, (Rank: Beyond Psychology, Gestaltung und Ausdruck, Modern Education, Practical Bearing of Psychoanalysis; Freud: 2 copies of Die Traumdeutung and English trans. of Group Psychology and the Analysis of the Ego; O.R.A. 1 (1) & 4 (2); Anais 7, 8, 9, 12 pages) (Box 40b)
    - Various authors including Taft, Robinson, Faatz Books by above authors inluding biography of Taft and Proceedings of First International Congress on Mental Hygiene, Various places, Various dates, (2 works by Taft, 2 by Robinson, 1 by Faatz, and 1 Proceedings pages) (Box 40c)
  - Subseries VI.4: Journals, Pamphlets, Brochures and Announcements
    - Psychiatry, [n.p.], May 1939, (160 page Journal) (Box 41, Folder 487)
    - Mental Hygiene, [n.p.], Jan. 1940, (174 pages) (Box 41, Folder 488)
    - American Imago, [n.p.], 1984, (100 page Journal) (Box 41, Folder 489)
    - Anais, [n.p.], 1988, (136 page Journal) (Box 41, Folder 490)
    - American Journal of Orthopsychiatry, [n.p.], Jan. 1940, (206 page Journal) (Box 41, Folder 491)
    - Journal of Analytical Psychology, London, 1998, (28 page Journal offprint.) (Box 41, Folder 491 A)
    - Die Schaubuhne, [n.p.], 1909, (18 page Journal) (Box 41, Folder 492)
    - First International Congress on Mental Hygiene, [n.p.], 1930, (70 page Brochure) (Box 41, Folder 493)
    - Dieheilige Urschrift der Menscheit, (4 page Brochure) (Box 41, Folder 494)
    - Weltgeschichte der Steinzeit, (6 page Brochure) (Box 41, Folder 495)
    - Vater und Sohn. Inzest-Motiv., [n.p.], 1912, (32 page pamphlet) (Box 41, Folder 495a)
    - Rank, Otto Psychoanalysis as General Psychology, [n.p.], 1926, (15 page Pamphlet) (Box 41, Folder 496)
    - Book announcements of Rank's works, (8 pages) (Box 41, Folder 497)
    - Book announcements of Rank's works, (5 pieces, 60 total pages) (Box 41, Folder 498)
- Series VII: Miscellaneous
  This series includes some correspondence, manuscripts by Rank and others, as well as some clippings and memorabilia, including Rank's Ph.D. diploma.
  - Subseries VII.1: General
    - Three envelopes addressed to Rank, (a.l.) (Box 42, Folder 499)
    - Freud, Sigmund [?] Vorlesungen. Notebook., (41 page a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 500)
    - Book receipts and book list. Mark Twain., [n.p.], 1933, (5 pages) (Box 42, Folder 501)
    - Rank, Otto Army Period. 1916-1918., [n.p.], 1916-1918, (19 page t.ms. &a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 502)
    - Rank, Otto Die Bedeutung der Psychoanalyse. Loose notes and post card., (15 page a.ms. &p.c.) (Box 42, Folder 503)
    - Rank, Otto Beziehung der Menschen zum Tier, (7 page t.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 504)
    - Rank, Otto Der eefolglose Sellst morder, [n.p.], 15 June 1929, (3 page a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 505)
    - Rank, Otto Dreams, (20 page a.ms. &t.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 506)
    - Rank, Otto Zur Genere der Genitalitat, (18 p (2 copies). t.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 507)
    - Rank, Otto [?] Kunstler [?], (6 page a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 508)
    - Rank, Otto Modern Education, (30 pages) (Box 42, Folder 509)
      [See arranged manuscripts 268 and 269]
    - Rank, Otto Mythen und Marchenforschung, (43 page a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 510)
    - Rank, Otto Mythen und Marchenforschung, (13 page t.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 511)
    - Rank, Otto Obituary. [Leopold Lowenfeld], [n.p.], Dec. 1923, (3 page a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 512)
    - Rank, Otto Poems. 1914-1917., [n.p.], 1914-1917, (17 page a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 513)
    - Rank, Otto Poems. 1917., [n.p.], 1917, (5 page a.ms. &t.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 514)
    - Rank, Otto Poems. 1903-1917. Copies and translations., [n.p.], 1903-1917, (50 page a.ms. &t.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 515)
    - Rank, Otto Proposed plan of a book, [n.p.], 13 May 1930, (23 page a.ms. &t.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 516)
    - Rank, Otto Zur psychanalytischen Bewegung in Frankreich, [n.p.], 1923, (4 page t.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 517)
    - Rank, Otto Das "Schauspiel" in "Hamlet", (18 page a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 518)
    - Rank, Otto Sexuality. Notes., (30 page a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 519)
    - Rank, Otto Der Sinn der Guiselda- fabel, [n.p.], 2 Jan. 1912, (26 page a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 520)
    - Rank, Otto Symbolik, (34 page a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 521)
    - Rank, Otto Symbolik. Notes., (4 page t.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 522)
    - Rank, Otto Todesproblem. Sexualitat., [n.p.], 9 Feb. to 3 May 1930, (25 page a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 523)
    - Rank, Otto To the ring which makes invisible, (5 page t.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 524)
    - Rank, Otto Mark Twain. Notes., (30 page a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 525)
    - Rank, Otto [?] Uber die Beeinflussung des Wachzustandes, (3 page t.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 526)
    - Rank, Otto Will, neurosis, death. Notes., (12 page a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 527)
    - Rank, Otto Women. Notes., (9 page a.ms.) (Box 42, Folder 528)
    - Rank, Otto Miscellaneous notes and articles, (3 page t.ms. &a.ms.) (Box 43, Folder 529)
    - Rank, Otto Miscellaneous notes and articles, (100 page a.ms. &t.ms.) (Box 43, Folder 530)
    - Rank, Otto Miscellaneous notes, (30 page a.ms.) (Box 43, Folder 531)
    - Rank, Otto Miscellaneous notes, (45 page a.ms. &clippings) (Box 43, Folder 532)
    - Rank, Otto Notes in French, (2 page t.ms.) (Box 43, Folder 533)
  - Subseries VII.2: Clippings
    - Rank, Otto Clipping on Freud and Rank, (4 page clipping) (Box 43, Folder 534)
    - Clippings, (14 page newspaper clippings) (Box 43, Folder 535)
    - Dickens clippings, (2 page magazine clipping) (Box 43, Folder 536)
    - Clippings. Army period 1916-1918., [n.p.], 1916-1918, (8 page newspaper and magazine clippings) (Box 43, Folder 537)
  - Subseries VII.3: Cataloged manuscripts
    - DeVoto, Bernard Mark Twain and the Genteel Tradition. [Harvard Graduates' Magazine], (10 page t.ms.) (Box 43, Folder 538)
    - DeVoto, Bernard The Mark Twain Papers. The Saturday Review of Literature., [n.p.], 20 Dec. 1938, (24 page Magazine) (Box 43, Folder 539)
  - Subseries VII.4: Miscellaneous
    - Drawing of Rank (Box 43, Folder 540)
    - Rank, Otto Ph. D. diploma, [n.p.], 1912 (Box 43, Folder 541)
      [See mapcase 14-12-3]
    - Rank, Otto Memorabilia, (4 pages) (Box 43, Folder 542)
- Series VIII: Gifts
  Gift of Gunther Stuhlmann- June 1996
  - Rank, Otto Art and Artist, New York / London: Norton, 1989, (431 pages) (Box 44)
  - Rank, Otto L' Art et L'Artiste, Paris: Payot, 1984, (328 pages) (Box 44)
  - Rank, Otto Il Trauma della Nascita, Florence: Guaraldi, 1972, (211 pages) (Box 44)
  - Rank, Otto Das Trauma der Geburt, Frankfurt: Fischer Pocket Books, 1988, (220 pages) (Box 44)
  - Rank, Otto Traum und Dichtung, Vienna: Turia & Kant, 1995, (79 pages) (Box 44)
  - Rank, Otto Der Doppelganger, Vienna: Turia & Kant, 1993, (129 pages) (Box 44)
  - Rank, Otto & S&or Ferenczi Entwicklungsziele der Psychoanalyse, Vienna: Turia & Kant, 1996, (95 pages) (Box 45)
  - Rank, Otto Volonte et Psychotherapie, Paris: Payot, 1976, (240 pages) (Box 45)
  - Rank, Otto Le Mythe de la Naissance du Heros, Paris: Payot, 1983, (345 pages) (Box 45)
  - Rank, Otto La Volonta di Essere Felici, Milana: Sugar Edicions, 1992, (180 pages) (Box 45)
  - Rank, Otto La figura del Don Giovanni, Milano: Sugar Edizione, 1987, (126 pages) (Box 45)
  - Rank, Otto Kunst und Kunstler, Paris, December 1930, (500 page Photocopies of a.ms. bound together) (Box 45)
    [Temporarily restricted. Require permission from Lieberman to use. Gift of Bertram Muller, 1998.]